[Music]
good evening ladies and gentlemen and
welcome to the Wall of Power Radio Hour
it is whistleblower week in Washington
DC this week and we have patriotic
whistleblower on who paid the price for
doing the right thing John kyaku is a
Greek American Author journalist and a
retired CIA intelligence officer he was
the senior investigator for the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee and a
consultant for ABC News he was also the
first government official in December of
2007 to tell the world that we were
water boarding al-Qaeda in secret
prisons he also turns out to be a man
I've known before I knew he was a CIA
agent as his brother Emanuel kyaku
played guitar with me from 1990 to 1992
John kirak kiraku thanks so much for
taking time to speak with us today oh
it's always good to speak with you Paul
thanks for having me you must uh uh have
been as uh as alarmed and in a way
excited
about uh the information that we're
coming across this week with the uh uh
The Whistleblower behind the Trump
Ukraine debacle and give us a little
insight into what your feeling is about
what's going on right now in real time
well I am excited but but maybe not for
the same reason that most Americans are
excited or many Americans are excited
I'm excited because all of the
mainstream media Outlets are using the
word whistleblower freely they're not uh
putting it on the screen with quotation
marks around it as they did uh in my
case you know when I first went public
with my Revelations on the cia's torture
program it took my attorneys a year to
convince the the news networks
specifically CNN Fox and MSNBC to stop
calling me CIA leaker John kiraku and to
start calling me CIA whistleblower John
kiraku and finally after a year after I
was convicted that converted to
whistleblower but then even after that
MSNBC at least uh kept quotation marks
around the word uh with Ed snowden's
Revelations it became a mainstream word
and um and now with this new CIA
whistleblower I'm glad to see that that
they're using it and before we get too
deep into the conversation Paul let me
let me tell your listeners too that
there is a legal definition of
whistleblowing it's very simple it's
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud abuse illegality or threats to the
public health or Public Safety a
whistleblower's motivation is irrelevant
if he meets those other requirements
he's a whistleblower
H uh will
you did what three years in in uh uh
federal prison for 20 23 months what
yeah a long long time uh it is John tell
uh you know we've had you on uh uh twice
before but it was a couple years ago so
we have new listeners that have been uh
listening to the wall and power radio
and for those that heard the first
couple of shows and would like to uh be
refreshed about your history tell the
people out there in wall Power Radio
Hour land how you uh became a CIA agent
and uh and and your motivations for
doing that sure um I was in graduate
school at George Washington University
here in Washington and I was taking a
class called uh the psychology of
leadership in which we had to uh as an
assignment we had to Shadow our bosses
for a week and write a psychological
evaluation about them I was working at a
labor union at the time the United Food
and Commercial Workers Union and my boss
was nuts and I was actually a little bit
afraid of him he was one of these old
school Union organizers he had had his
back broken by scab
in a strike one of these old school guys
and so I'm uh I'm shadowing him and at
one point in the middle of the week we
had an an argument and I called him a
racist which he was and he he got so
angry he set a stance and he put his
fists up and I actually recoiled I
remember recoiling because I thought oh
here it comes but instead of punching me
he blurts out my penis is bigger than
yours and I looked at him and I said I
quit you're nuts and I quit and I walked
out well I wrote this up in my paper and
I gave it back to my professor and uh
and a week later he sent me the paper
back and um gave me an A and then wrote
in the in the margin please see me after
class wow so I went to see him after
class he asked me to follow him down to
his office he closed the door and uh and
he turns and he looks at me and he said
listen I'm not really a professor here
I'm a CIA officer undercover as a
professor here I'm looking for people
who might fit into the cia's culture
would you like to work for the CIA wow
and I was recruited so I went from grad
school to the CIA John I just want to
jump in here and say my boss is nuts too
and I'm
self-employed oh that gonna use
that please do John that must have been
an incredible moment for you
it was incredible because it really was
clandestine you know there was so much
more to the story I I had to uh I had to
go to an unmarked office building in
Rosland Virginia I was interviewed by a
guy who never told me his name and uh
and then I had to go to an unmarked
building in Vienna Virginia I was
interviewed by a psychologist a
psychiatrist and an anthropologist they
asked me crazy questions like describe
your relationship with your mother or
have you ever betrayed a friendship or
uh was your father the disciplinarian in
the family and then they told me uh to
go into the next room and give them some
some hair some piss and some blood and
next thing I knew I was in man oh man oh
man now did they tell you while you're
going through these preliminary uh
procedures uh before you became a
Bonafide CIA
agent not to tell anybody what you're
doing yeah I couldn't tell anybody and I
said listen I'm going to have to tell my
wife because I had I had gotten engaged
the year earlier and and I got married
during the process and they said tell
your wife but don't tell anybody else
wow and I didn't I didn't well you know
John it was so I remember the night and
I believe it was December 2017 when you
came out and uh uh and said that we were
uh illegally water boarding Al-Qaeda
prisoners overseas and I was watching
the uh I believe it was on I believe I
saw on ABC News and I saw your picture
and with your name John kyaka go oh my
God that's emanuel's brother I met I Met
You John at emanuel's uh uh wedding in
Newcastle Pennsylvania along with your
lovely uh family and it blew my
mind it was a crazy uh day to tell you
the truth I thought that I was just sort
of stating the obvious I didn't expect
it to be this major International story
I was the front page of of every
newspaper every major newspaper in the
world the next day and um and it opened
up a Pandora's Box that I've never been
able to uh get closed again let's go
back uh to because the stories you told
on the last couple shows were so phenom
phal so what was your first mission as a
CIA uh
operative my first overseas mission was
to go to uh TF Saudi Arabia right after
the invasion of Kuwait most of the
members of the royal family of Kuwait
had escaped uh to Saudi Arabia and they
set up a government in Exile in TF which
is um in the mountains north of jeda
Saudi Arabia and so I was an expert on
the crazy as it sounds I was an expert
on the Kuwaiti royal family what year
was this John what year was this this
was 1990 so the the invasion of Kuwait
was was August of 1990 I went to tyf in
October of 1990 really to liaz with a
Kuwaiti resistance and to try to Buck up
the royal family and get them ready for
war huh and you know crazy as it sounds
I was 25 years old wow and I'm meeting
I'm meeting with the king and the Crown
Prince and then the king is crying the
crown is you know depressed and then I
have to go back and and report all this
and it's these reports were going
directly to the president because he was
friendly with the King and and I'm
saying he's crying and he's talking
about his Rose Garden that the Iraqis
have dug up his Rose Garden he's not
making any sense like I don't know what
to do huh so I tried to befriend the man
and try to C him and say look you know I
know I'm young but I'm telling
you it's it's not unusual for countries
to go to war it's highly unusual for
countries to go to war with us we've
made a commitment that we're going to
liberate this country and I I had to
keep repeating it as a mantra to all of
these royal family members they were
just despondent wow and I said no no
we're going to get you your country back
just hang on did they know you were
working with the CIA or did you have to
have a cover to while you were doing
that um I had a light cover just for
travel purposes but they they knew I was
CIA I went out there as a CIA
officer did do did you feel on your
first mission and I know and we're going
to talk about that alqa number three
that you personally arrested in bed in
the middle of the night and in a few
other Capers you were a part of but when
you first got into it you're 25 years
old you must have been in a way kind of
fearless I mean I would think you'd have
to
be you know the only other person who
ever asked me that question was my mom
um and it's a good question and the
truth is Paul that you are so busy and
you are so focused on the mission that
you're really not thinking of being
afraid you're not thinking of the danger
I I can get into more detail when we
talk about Al-Qaeda and Pakistan but you
know looking back I think to myself what
was I insane like I should have been I
should have been frightened I should
have been worried about my safety tell
you a story um if we have you know what
yeah let's let's wait for the the second
part I just want to jump in here John
because we've only got about 20 seconds
left in this segment on the wall of par
radio but your mother was an absolute
Delight she reminded me of my mother and
I got to be able to hump your dad's
equipment he was a great piano player
was a 4our gig and then help him go home
in about 3 or 4 in the morning more with
John kyaku on wall power radio hour
after these messages
[Music]
breaking rocks in the hot sun I bought
the LA law one I bought the law law one
I needed money cuz I had nought
the welcome back to the wall power this
is your host Paul metah my guest for the
whole show tonight retired CIA operative
John kyaku John at the end of the last
segment you were talking about uh what
it took in terms of being Fearless to
get into the whole CIA World tell us
more about that through an awful lot of
training right I mean when when I first
when I first went into operations uh I
was sent the CIA sent me to their uh
training facility in the South it's
colloquially known as the farm and in
the handgun I took handgun uh courses
and explosives courses and counter
terrorist driving courses in the handgun
course the instructor in the very first
meeting he said does does anybody here
not own a gun and I put my hand up and I
looked around and I was the only one
whose hand was up and he said you don't
own a gun and I said truth be told I've
never actually touched a gun incredible
and said oh my God he says okay we're
going to start at the beginning well
eight weeks later um I was decorated for
Marksmanship I had a knack for it just a
natural ability and I actually went into
competitive ski shooting I was so
good but I
had that's
incredible I had good teachers and then
they moov you from there into
explosives uh and then from explosives
into lots and lots of driving courses so
when you go over let's let's let's hear
about these driving
courses yeah yeah they send you out to
uh to the desert north of Las Vegas and
um you you start you start in small
towns you move to cities and you do
these uh these exercises on ranges that
the CIA either owns or contracts and
you're crashing through roadblocks and
you're crashing through you know through
well I I probably shouldn't say exactly
what you're crashing through you crash
through a lot of stuff to the point
where I actually got injured and I had
to have my knee replaced um but this is
serious crashing right I guess so and
yeah yeah I've got the nasty scars to to
prove it uh and then they send you out
to the desert in uh in Nevada to do the
uh the counterterrorism part so they
teach you how to you know Drive in sand
and drive over dunes and how to get out
of a dirt Road Village when somebody's
trying to kill you and you know you
internalize it Paul and it becomes a
normal part of your your way of of
living and so you're you're overseas in
these dangerous areas or in some cases
what are called denied areas places
where Americans aren't really supposed
to be and um and you're driving like a
normal person because you know that if
if it hits the fan in one Split Second
you're going to fall back on your
training and you're going to be able to
get out of there now I have to think
though when you're over in the states
training knowing nobody uh no bad guys
were chasing you driving through the
dunes driving really fast doing the
sharp must been kind of fun for a little
bit you know it's it's fun except you do
a lot of vomiting like you know to drive
anymore yeah it's not your turn to drive
anymore so you get in the back seat
while your buddy can drive and Bo the
windows better be open
it's like sounds sounds like something
in the 70s when I was coming home from
rock concerts but anyway um so uh you
get all this training so how long does
the training uh routine
last well it depends if if you go into
operations as soon as they hire you it
lasts about 18 months uh for the it
lasted about a year yeah it's a it's a
long time I didn't need the whole CIA
101 course because I had already been in
the CIA as an analyst for seven years
before I switched to counterterrorism
operations so I knew what the CIA did I
know I knew who did what and what
offices handled what issues I didn't
need to do all that stuff I just needed
the Hands-On operational training and
I'm glad I did because when I finally
got to to Pakistan it saved my life H
let's talk a little bit because that's
an incredible story you've got a couple
incredible stories uh concerning uh
handguns and bad guys but uh so what was
as this CIA analyst what did that
entail yeah you know it's pretty simple
you um you become the expert the US
government's leading expert on an issue
and you sit in a cubicle in Langley
Virginia and think the big thoughts and
you write papers for the president the
secretaries of state and defense the
National Security advisor and then you
sort of jet around the world as your
expertise is needed wow um I I had the
curse of uh of speaking
Arabic and so uh I was rarely needed in
London and Paris and Rome I was usually
needed in Yemen and Sudan
and lovely vacation destinations like
that when did you all learn to speak
Arabic um the CIA taught me to speak
Arabic um let's see I started in
1993 I did I did a year uh at a at the
CIA language school and then I went to
Tunis to to learn uh golf dialect Arabic
and then I spent two years in Bahrain um
as it's a little tiny country in the
Persian Gulf just off the coast of Saudi
Arabia same size and same population as
Pittsburgh and uh I was the head of the
US embassy's economic section there well
it must have kind of worked for you
being a Greek American with kind of
olive skin and dark hair you kind of had
some of those qualities of of those
people uh so blending in ability to
blend in yeah I can blend in in a lot of
places around around the world H so when
did your uh when did you start being the
analyst and how long did that take
before the counter uh
terrorism I I started as an analyst and
um and I did that uh let's see from 1990
to 97 I went into the counterterrorism
operational training in 97 through 98
and then I was in Greece from
99 from 98 to 2000 uh doing
counterterrorism operations and and that
was that was trial by fire or I should
say baptism by fire because people don't
realize or didn't realize at the time
Greece was one of the most dangerous
places in the world to be an official
American we spent more money on on
security and counterterrorism in Athens
than we spent in Beirut uh there was a a
group called revolutionary organiz ation
17 November which had killed our station
Chief Two of our defense attaches a
couple of soldiers there was an
Associated group called Popular
revolutionary struggle that killed
dozens and dozens of Greek
policemen and um and they targeted the
American Embassy as well and that was uh
that was the first attempt on my life
was in Athens I had to be evacuated in
August of 2000 and that
particular uh I know you're very proud
of your Greek Heritage that must have
been a fighting hard to take yeah it's
hard to take but it must have must have
been a very
personal oh boy yeah it was very
personal because you know I've been to
Greece a million times before being
assigned there and you go and and the
beaches are beautiful and the islands
are beautiful and the food is great and
the people are friendly but when you're
living there as an official American
especially as a CIA officer working on
uh on terror ISM issues uh it's a
completely different world uh you know I
I was specifically working against this
group 17 November hey John hold on for
one second we've just got a few seconds
left in the second uh segment here we've
got John kako retired CIA agent on the
air and uh I want you to continue that
story working in Greece and then we got
to get to Pakistan and then when things
get really nuts John kyaku I'm Paul mits
and the wall and Power Radio Hour back
in a bit
Power
Radio welcome back ladies and gentlemen
to the Wall of Power Radio Hour this is
your host Paul metah my guest for the
whole show is a man who has a storied
history working with the CIA spent some
time in prison as a whistleblower and
happens to be a very good friend of mine
John kyaku at the end of the last
segment on the Well ower Radio you were
telling us about working against a
particular terrorist organization in
your in Greece right it was called
revolutionary organization 17 November
and uh what is 17 November what does
that what does that signify ah yes on
the 17th of November
1973 uh the military hun that ruled
Greece at the time drove tanks onto uh
the grounds of the University there the
Athens poly Technic University and open
fire on unarmed students the government
says they killed 38 students the
students say that more than 500 were
killed and um it was that event that led
to the downfall of the uh of the
military government and the
reinstitution of of a democratic
government in
Greece November 17th is also happens to
be the uh uh uh birth birth date of one
of the greatest Electric Blues guitar
players of all time who became a friend
of mine Hubert sumlin who played guitar
with Allin W for years but that's uh uh
beside the point but but I remember when
you said November 17th I go oh yeah that
date uh reminds me of something but
anyway uh back to John
kyaku so I had a a new neighbor move in
uh sort of caty corner from from me he
turned out to be the British defense at
he was a brigadier general by the name
of Steven Saunders and a couple of weeks
after he moved in we were at a dinner
party together and he was jokingly
making fun of me because I drove an
armored car and I always carried two
guns one on my ankle and one in a
holster under my jacket and so he was
making fun and he said you Americans
you're so obsessed with security he said
look around you this is an EU country
it's a NATO country what are you so
afraid of and I said semi jokingly in
response you Brits live in a dream world
if you think that because they have palm
trees and pretty beaches they're not
going to kill you well you know what if
they have the chance they're gonna kill
you wow and two weeks later they killed
him oh my goodness gra way to work holy
cow yeah he was I was a quarter of a
mile behind him in my car I didn't see
it happen but I was able to report on on
the aftermath from traffic that's a
that's a long story what we can talk
about a different time but the reason
why this affected me directly was
because whenever November whenever 17
November would do a hit they would leave
a u a a Manifesto or a communic either
at the site of the hit or they would
hide one and then call a friendly
newspaper and tell them where it is well
they left one at the site of the hit and
in it they
said it means we saw the big spy but we
knew that he was armed and he was in an
armored car and we elected to carry out
the Revolutionary sentence on the war
criminal Saunders well as soon as they
released this this Manifesto my boss
called me and he said hey they were
after you this morning I said what I
said no my tradecraft is excellent I
said I have eyes on the back of my head
he said no they knew your car they knew
you had a gun they were watching you he
said you have to get out of here I get
to the Embassy and um and they were
waiting for me my my colleagues were
waiting for me they put me in a
different armored car another armored
car went up and picked up my wife and
two sons we met at the airport and we
were on the 12:00 flight to New York and
then the embassy went and packed us out
I don't know how they I unless they were
watching Saunders and stumbled on to me
I I've never been able to figure out how
they were able to find me because I
really was conscious of my personal
security but it was a close call it was
it was one of two attempts on my life in
my
career number one it must have felt
great to get back with your family safe
and sound on American
soil well my wife left me in part
because of that whole incident oh wow so
yeah I was I was home uh on American
soil so I could hire a divorce attorney
and that's that's the way it working out
I don't mean to laugh I'm not laughing
at you I'm laughing with you John you
know people ask you know she go ahead
she said listen I I can't live like this
this isn't a normal life so she said I'm
going back to Ohio I'm taking the kids
that was the end of it you know people
uh they ask me they go meta have you
ever been married and I said no but I've
never been divorced either so there you
go there you go you know what there's
something to be said for that oh my
goodness gracious well I live uh
vicariously I've got great nephews and
nieces said so what I'm missing in
family I enjoy with uh my friends like
you uh and uh that have successful kids
and Liv so uh I I lead a full life that
way John tell us about the second time
the second uh attempt on your life well
um a friend of mine who was a station
Chief in a Middle Eastern country uh
emailed me one day we have a classified
email system at the CIA and he said look
we've recruited a guy and it turns out
he's a double AG
and it's too dangerous for my people to
meet with him because he doesn't know
that we know he's a double agent working
for one of our greatest uh enemies in
the world he said could you pretend to
be me and come out here and handle this
guy and I said that I could it sounds
like an exciting prospect something
totally different yeah but when they say
handle what exactly do they mean so
handle means meet with a guy extract
intelligence from him but all the while
don't tip him off that we know that he's
really not working for us so there's
there's a lot of there's a lot of
security and Counter Intelligence that
goes into this counter terrorism was my
specialty not Counter Intelligence so
this was a real learning experience and
it it ended up resulting in me becoming
the chief of Counter Intelligence for
the cia's counter terrorism Center
anyway that's a i i digress you're a
badass John kyaku let me tell you that
right now wow I'm impressed it was a
crazy life yeah so I I fly out to the
Middle East I actually made 25 trips to
the Middle East in the in the year after
the September 11th attacks and um I
would meet with this guy and I would
give him instructions and task him and
and he would give me intelligence pass
me intelligence and then we would we
would follow him with a team of of uh
surveillance and they would follow him
right back to this enemy country's
Embassy and so
finally uh our friends in Maryland told
me that they were on to me and um and I
was really really careful again but
there was nothing I could have done
about this this was inevitable they were
going to figure out that I wasn't who I
said I was and they said to him look we
know who the CIA station Chief is and
it's not him so he said well what do you
want me to do and they told him we want
to kill him in the next meeting so I got
a cable from headquarters and they said
abort the operation and they told me why
I said absolutely not I said this guy's
afraid of his own shadow he's not gonna
kill me in the next meeting I said I can
take him down before he even realizes
what's happening wow and this became a
back and forth between headquarters and
me and and the station was very
supportive of my position because they
had invested so much in the operation so
I said 'l every hotel room in the world
is the same you walk in and the bathroom
is right there by the door right and
then farther in is the room is the
bedroom so I said let's just get two
rooms that are connected we can have our
liaison friends in the Next Room I'm
going to leave the door open so when the
guy knocks I'm gonna say come in I'm
going to be in the bathroom he comes in
I'm going to take him down the other
Arabs are going to bust through the side
door and everybody's gonna be happy so
except that guy except that guy and boy
he wasn't happy Paul let me tell you so
sure enough this enemy country they have
six officers doing surveillance in the
lobby we had four doing surveillance in
the lobby so they're all staring at each
other down there and um and he comes up
to the to the room and he knocks on the
door and I said come in and he comes in
and I dart out of the bathroom and I
just tackle and I take him down I
wrestle the gun away from him he was
trying to get the gun out of his
waistband but I got the gun and my Arab
colleagues came in from the side and I'm
sitting on this guy and he's swearing at
me and I said did you think I was so
stupid did you think I was such an
amateur that I didn't know that you were
coming here tonight to kill me I said
what's the matter with you shame on you
show some
respect you know talking to he's like
I'm going to kill you I'm going to kill
your family and I was like yeah yeah
yeah so my Arab Co colleagues uh gave
him a
shot and he was out we wrapped him up in
a sheet we had an ambulance waiting we
took him out the back door as a dead
body because people die in hotels every
day sure and and what you do is you just
wrap them up you put them on a gurnie
and you take him out the b right that's
what we did well when he woke up he was
he was tied to a chair
uh and cuffed behind his back in the
chair in this country's intelligence
service and I said now it's time for you
to start
talking and so um the the enemy country
they they never figured out what
happened to him wow because they were
all down in the lobby waiting for him to
come back out after he killed me and he
never came back out
incredible John kyaka this is
so you describe these stories in such
detail I could see him in my my mind's
eye and it's it's like uh man there's
got to be I hope you're working on the
uh uh the film script for your life
because this is really you know the
funny thing Paul what a tough industry I
sold the rights to it three different
times to Universal 20th Century Fox and
Paramount and all three let it lapse
because they said that there was so much
detail and there were so many stories
that they just couldn't cram it into two
hours wow well you got to of you've got
yeah I'm sure well it should be you know
think I mean I'm being serious here you
should think Netflix you know with these
series you know six8 10 episodes I mean
it's
incredible yeah thank you Sean uh before
we get to the last segment here we got
uh about a minute and a half left tell
people how they can uh uh follow you uh
get your books etc etc thanks thank you
yeah uh I'm on Facebook and and Twitter
uh John kiraku K i i a kouu also John
kiraku dcom I've got um uh the only
existing hardback copies of my first
book which which did well it made number
five on the New York Times bestsellers
list and uh there are a lot of great
stories in there that's at John kiraku
dcom um yeah so otherwise I'm pretty
much on all the social platforms and you
have a radio sh too right I do here in
the Washington DC area on uh let's see
105.5 FM and 1390 a.m. it's called loud
and clear uh by the end of the evening
it's also up on uh iHeart Radio uh
spreer uh iTunes Spotify cool loud and
clear you know what Jen I was in uh
Memphis for the Blues Awards as my buddy
uh Willie walk was nominated for five or
six Blues Awards and I was standing on
the corner of the Lorraine
Motel and talking to this yeah an that
that's a whole show right there that
experience yeah I I made that pilgrimage
once too it's incredible but I was uh
speaking with this uh gentleman and his
uh girlfriend or wife he was a guy named
Chris plant he's a right-wing talk show
host in DC you ever heard of him no I
don't know him yeah anyway we don't need
to give him any more uh props more with
John Kaku after these messages
let it all go set it all
free you let the whole wide world
see exactly what is going
on exactly who's looking
on stories start to they col your name
welcome back ladies and gentlemen to the
Wall of Power Radio Hour this is your
host Paul metah my guest and friend on
for the whole night tonight it's just
been a fabulous show I'm so enjoying
enjoying it retired CIA operative John
kiraku now John you told the story in
one of our last shows we've had you on
twice but it's such a dynamic story I'd
love to have you tell it again when you
got uh when you got Al-Qaeda number
three out of bed at gunpoint in the
middle of the night the middle of the
night indeed uh it was late March of
2002 I was the chief of counter
terrorism operations for the CIA in
Pakistan and uh we got word that Abu
zubeda was somewhere in Pakistan and we
had to catch him um but the the problem
there is Pakistan is the size of Texas
and it has it has 180 million people in
it and you can't just say he's somewhere
in Pakistan go catch him so it took me
about six weeks before I was able to
finally narrow it down I I asked
headquarters to send in a what's called
a targeting analyst to help me uh you
know I told you earlier that as an
analyst I was thinking the big thoughts
and writing papers for the president a
targeting analyst has a completely
different job his job is to just go
through through metadata Reams reams of
data sometimes thousands hundreds of
thousands of pages of data to fi to try
to find somebody to try to to geolocate
them usually so we can either kill him
with a drone or snatch him with a with a
Seal Team so um we brought in uh one of
the best targeting analysts in the CIA
who happened to be a friend of mine and
um he worked on it for several weeks and
then finally he came to me and he said
look I can't narrow this down to any
fewer than 14 sites he could be in any
one of these 14 sites I don't have any
idea which one it is well we had never
done more than two raids in one night
before you know you break down the door
of two places simultaneously you grab
everybody inside and then you
interrogate them and how many let me
just ask you quickly John so when you do
something like that how many uh Navy
SEALS or or the CIA operatives or how
many people are on a mission like that
at one time on on a normal Mission if
you're if you're hitting one target it's
one CIA officer uh maybe two uh one or
two FBI a agents and then as many people
as the pakistanis want to bring and and
the pakistanis always brought a a whole
party to these things so five six eight
Pakistani Special Forces
guys but then for this thing 14 sites I
I cabled headquarters and I said listen
I need a lot of stuff I said I need guns
I need ammunition I need night vision
goggles I need secure Communications and
I
need well several million dollars in
cash
because there are a lot of people that
are going to need to be paid off so
um most importantly in that cable I said
I need a I need a big team so they sent
me 36 people on a chartered 737 it uh it
landed the next day half CIA half FBI we
divided everybody up and we decided
we're going to hit every single one of
these places at exactly 2 a.m. so we
reconed at the uh at a safe house I had
purchased and um and around 10 o'clock I
stood on the on the coffee table and I
said listen at the risk of sounding
melodramatic we're g to have to
synchronize our watches so we
synchronized our watches and um you know
there were some Chuckles and I said
here's what we're going to do 0130
everybody leaves their safe houses 0145
be in place 0150 make sure you have
direct line of sight and you're ready to
go
0158 get out of your car
at exactly 0200 break down the door we
had battering rams I said grab all the
men and separate the women and children
from the men so to make a long story
short that's what we did now there was
one of these sites in particular where
we couldn't break down the door because
it was a steel reinforced door like
imported from Germany so we worked on
that dog on door for 20 minutes and I
could hear it in the distance I was on
the roof of the of the safe house and I
said to a colleague of mine that's not
good and then we heard shots fired I
said well that's definitely not good so
we jumped in a car we drove over to the
site and it was
chaos so I said to one of the pakistanis
I said what happened and he said we got
him we got your man and I said where is
he and he points to this guy who's like
he looked to me to be dead M and um and
I said that doesn't look anything like
the the guy we were looking for the
pakistanis never knew who the target was
we were afraid they would they would
leak it to him and help him Escape so we
only called him the big fish and that
became Mr Fish so he said this is your
Mr Fish and I said that's definitely not
Mr fish so I called the analyist I said
listen they shot these three guys one of
them's Dead one of them is almost dead
and the other one is screaming his
bloody head off I said what do I do and
he says give me a a picture of his eye
I'll run a retinal scan so I shouted at
him hyic open your eyes but his eyes
were rolled back in his head and like I
say he was so severely wounded he he was
really on the brink of death right so I
said he can't open his eyes and I can't
get him get his eyes open they're rolled
back in his head John we've got about
one we've got about one minute left so
keep but tell the story just give give
me a picture of his ear so I got a
picture of his ear sent it to the
Embassy the embassy sent it to
headquarters
it was him we put him on a plane two
nights later he went to a secret site
and he's been locked up ever since John
kyaku that was one of the most
incredible stories I've ever heard and I
have to say after five and a half years
of interviewing great people with great
stories on the Walla Power Radio Hour
you just jumped with that story the way
it was told to the top of the list my
brother oh thank you thank you Paul it's
a it's a real pleasure no it's it's been
great John I need I want to ask you uh
one question here with a minute we have
left I have a friend of mine that served
in the Vietnam War and when he got back
and he was the middle of everything of
fighting and all kinds of dangerous
stuff his life back in the States though
he was safe and sound he missed the
thrill of what he was going through did
did have you ever had that those sort of
feelings oh oh I still missed the thrill
I I think about it every single day and
I resigned from the CIA 15 years ago and
I still think about it every single day
I miss it very much for all of you out
there in the Walla Power Radio Hour land
check out John kako his
story uh the 20 uh some months he did in
the prison for doing the right thing
he's one of the Great American Patriots
a really great guy as you can tell from
this interview uh in intelligent and
balls the size of Mexico John thank you
so much and uh oh it's always great to
speak with you and you have a wonderful
weekend brother we'll talk to you soon
fantastic Paul thanks you too thanks for
listening to the Wall of Power Radio
Hour this show is produced by Paul metah
engineered by Brett Johnson and we'd
like to thank Our Guest John kyaka what
an exciting show it was I've got a bunch
of shows myself coming up celebrating my
40th Ann in town culminating with a big
show Skyway to Hell 40 at the Parkway
Theater on December 23rd with a bunch of
my favorite musicians go to Paul mea.com
for more info and like my dad used to
tell me remember to be kind and make
someone happy
[Music]